- [Narrator] Now that we have our offset path
assigned to our element, it's time to animate it.
Just to recap, our robot is an image in our HTML
and in our CSS we've assigned an offset path
to our robot image.
There are a few different properties
that work along with the offset path property,
but the two that are most useful for animation
are the offset distance and the offset rotation.
Offset distance represents how far along the offset path
the element in question is,
you can use this to place a number of elements
spaced out along a particular path, or in our case,
we'll use it to move an element along a path
by animating it's offset distance value.
I'll start by writing a set of key frames to animate
that offset distance value.
I'm going to call this set of key frames fly
because that's kind of what the robot will be doing,
and I'll start at the 0% key frame with an offset distance
of 0%.
So that is 0% of the way along the path,
effectively the start of the path.
And I'll create a 100% key frame with an offset distance
of 100%, which is all the way across to the end of the path.
This will make whichever element we apply this to
animate from the very start of the path
to the very end of the path.
I should note that the key frame percentages
and the offset distance percentages
don't have to match exactly.
It's just how it worked out for this particular example.
With those key frames in place,
we can assign those key frames to our robot image.
So I'll give our robot image the animation of fly.
I'm going to give it a duration of nine seconds
because it's got a lot of ground to cover.
I'm going to use a custom cubic bezier for the easing
and I'll give it an animation film mode of both,
that way it will stay at the end of the path
once it's animated to that offset distance of 100%.
If we save this in preview it now,
our robot animates along the path we set as the offset path
and that's pretty cool.
You'll notice that our robot image is rotating
as it goes along the path,
and that's because the offset rotate property
is set to auto by default.
So we didn't set an offset rotate property,
but right now it's as if we wrote this
and that will make the element that's following the path
auto rotate to keep itself oriented to the path.
If we wanted to, we can add an angle in addition
to this auto.
So I could add, let's say an additional 45 degrees,
which essentially says follow the path
with the offset rotate of auto, but lean forward
just by 45 degrees in addition to that.
So if we save that in preview our robot again,
now we have the robot following along the path
but leaning just a little bit forward
and maybe that's a kind of fun effect,
I don't know, I think personally I prefer
just the straight up auto value,
but I wanted to show you that there were some options
there as well.
So I'll go back to auto and preview our robot once more,
and our robot animates along the path in that loop shape.
As I mentioned, offset path is still a fairly new property
and it will most definitely be evolving.
It can also be a bit tricky when you have to use
the SVG path syntax.
Animating with offset path is definitely something
worth knowing about and trying out for yourself,
but at the time of recording,
it's not something I'd recommend using in production,
at least not until it's more widely supported by browsers.