- [Instructor] CSS custom properties,
otherwise known as CSS variables,
make it possible to create key frames
that are more dynamic and flexible.
In the earlier days of web animation,
one drawback of CSS key frame animation
was the fact that you couldn't change
or alter the key frames once they were written.
CSS variables change all of that.
In short,
CSS variables allow you to define and reuse
your own custom values within your CSS.
There are a number of things
that make CSS variables different than,
say, preprocessor variables that you might've used before.
But three things that really stand out
are the fact that they can be changed at runtime,
they follow the CSS cascade,
and they can be easily accessed by JavaScript.
When it comes to animation,
we can use CSS variables
both in our key frame definitions
and when we're assigning animation properties
to individual elements.
So there's a lot of potential for flexibility.
Let's take a look at all of this in action
and use one set of key frames
and create four words that animate in in different ways.
To start out our example,
I have a set of key frames
that transforms elements along the X axis
from somewhere far off to the left
with a scale of one and no rotation
to a place exactly where they would normally be
with a scale of 1.5 and a rotation of 10 degrees.
I've applied this animation to all of my paragraphs
with the same duration and the same easing.
That means when I go to preview our files so far,
we'll see this,
all four of my paragraphs animate in
with the exact same animation
and start and end in the exact same place.
Now if I wanted all four of these words to animate in
in slightly different ways,
I could write four different animations,
one for each word,
or I could use CSS variables
to make my key frames more dynamic
and adjust the animation slightly for each different word.
And that's the route I'm going to take for this example.
So I'll head back to my CSS
and start adding some CSS variables to use.
I'm going to start by declaring some CSS variables
at the root of my document.
And since my animation is moving things a certain distance
scaling to a certain scale amount
and rotating to a certain number of degrees,
those are the three things I'll make variables for first.
So I'll make a CSS variable of distance or dist rather,
and I will set its default at 0%.
I'll create a CSS variable of scale,
and I'll set its default at two.
I'll create a CSS variable degrees
or deg, I guess, is how you might say that,
and I will set that default to 10 degrees.
With those all set,
I'll go and reference them in my key frames.
So at my 100% key frame,
instead of translating to 0%,
I'll translate to the variable of distance or dist,
as I wrote above,
And instead of scaling to the hard-coded number of 1.5,
I'll scale to my variable of scale.
And the same for rotation.
And now that I have those variable set
for my 100% key frame,
I can adjust those variables
for each individual paragraph thanks to the CSS cascade.
I'll start with my first paragraph
and adjust some or all of these variable values
for each of my paragraphs
so that the visual results of the 100% key frame
will be slightly different for each.
So starting with my first paragraph,
I'll give it the scale variable value of 1.75.
I'll give it the dist variable value of 80%
and the degree of variable value of five degrees.
So changing all of the values,
at least slightly,
for our first paragraph.
For our second paragraph,
I'm not going to change all of the values for this one.
I'll let one of them use the default value
set up at the root.
So I will give it the scale variable value of 1.5.
And I will give it the dist variable value of 30%.
I haven't given my second paragraph a degree variable value.
So that means it will default to use the one
that set up here in my root,
which will be the degree rotation of 10 degrees.
I'm sure you're starting to see
the power of CSS variables here.
For my third paragraph,
I'm going to let it use
the root value of the scale variable,
but I'll give it a degree variable of minus five degrees,
so the rotation will be slightly different
than the ones above.
And then I'll give it the distance variable of 100%.
Last but not least,
I will give my fourth paragraph
the scale variable value of 1.9,
the deg or degree variable value of 15 degrees.
And I think I'll leave it at that.
So if I save our file now
and preview what we've got,
all four words are still animating in
with the same duration, the same easing,
but their ending point is visually different,
because we've used those CSS variables
to change the 100% key frame values
for each of those paragraphs.
That's already pretty great,
but we can make our animations even more dynamic
if we use variables in our animation assignment
as well as in the key frames.
So let's go back to our CSS and do a little of that.
I'm going to go back to where I define my variables
at the root.
And I'm going to add three variables
we can use for our animation assignment.
Specifically, that will be a dur or duration variable.
And I'll set that by default at two seconds,
since that's already what we have
in our animation assignment.
I'll create a delay variable,
and I will set that default value to zero seconds.
And I'll create an ease variable
and give it the default value of linear.
Next, I'll use those variables in our animation assignment
that we've assigned to all of our paragraphs.
So for example,
here I have the duration of two seconds in the shorthand,
and I can replace that
with the variable of dur or duration.
I don't have a delay set on this currently,
but I could add a variable for delay here.
The second number with time in the animation shorthand
will be the delay,
and that counts the same when we're using variables as well.
And last but not least,
I will replace our linear easing with our easing variable.
So that means that the variable values
will be used in place of the hard-coded numbers and easing
I had here before.
Just like we did with our 100% key frame variables,
we can adjust the value of these variables
for each of our individual paragraphs,
and that will give us even more of a dynamic look
to our animations.
So for paragraph one,
I'm going to give it a different duration of,
say, 1.9 seconds.
It'll be a little bit faster than the rest.
And I will give it a custom easing with the ease variable,
and that will be a cubic Bezier.
For paragraph two,
I'll give it a delay variable value of maybe 0.5 seconds,
just a little bit of a delay.
And I'm going to give it an easing variable value
of its own cubic Bezier as well.
For paragraph three,
let's just give it a different easing value.
So we'll use the ease variable
and give it a cubic Bezier value as well.
And I'll do the same for our fourth paragraph as well.
With those additions in place,
we can save and preview our file once again.
And as you can see,
with those additional variables,
we've made the animation even more different
for each individual word.
They're all still using the same set of key frames
and the same animation assignment.
But thanks to our CSS variables,
they've all got a slightly different look.
And this is just the start
of how we can make our CSS animations
even more dynamic with CSS variables.
We could take this even further by using JavaScript
to change the values of these variables at runtime,
and even more.
So CSS variables are really wonderful
when they're paired with CSS animation.
If you found this example interesting,
I highly recommend learning more about CSS variables
and the powerful things they can do.