- [Instructor] Variable fonts are a game changer
for web typography.
A variable font is a font file that is able to store
a continuous range of design variants
and we can animate those variants with CSS.
The key to animating variable fonts
is the font-variation-settings property.
We can animate any access of variation
defined in the font itself
with the font-variation-settings property.
The variants available to animate
will vary from font to font
and a site like wakamaifondue.com
can help show you the options that are available
for any given variable font.
For example, if I drop a copy
of the Recursive variable font on the site,
it will give me this report of all the characteristics
and variable axes available in this particular font.
I can even test them out right here
to see what they look like.
Many fonts will show their variable properties
on their websites as well like Recursive does here.
Looking at the demo section of the page,
we can see that Recursive has five axes of variation,
mono, casual, weight, slant, and cursive.
Each axis has its own four-letter name
and each of these can take a range of values
as shown in the demo.
As those values change,
the appearance of the font changes
and the font-variation-settings property
lets us animate those value changes.
Let's go look at some of this in action in our own CSS.
I'm using the same font we just looked at, Recursive,
here in my example.
Let's animate some of the variable aspects of Recursive
with a key frame animation.
So I'll write my key frame block
and I'll name this animation VARS
since we're animating a variable font.
I'll start with my 0% key frame
and this is where I can start to use
the font-variation-settings property.
We know from its site that Recursive has axes
for casual, cursive, weight, and slant.
I'll use these in the font-variation-settings
to create my animation.
So we'll start with the font-variation-settings property.
And first, I'll use the name
of the casual axis which is CASL
and start with a value of one.
Then onto the cursive axis which is CRSV.
Give that a value of one as well.
And for weight which is WGHT,
we'll go with 300.
And slant which is SLNT.
We'll give that a value of zero.
I'm going to go on
and add a couple more key frames for 25% and 75%
with different settings in the font-variation-settings
just for a little variation in our animation.
At 25, I'll set the casual axis to zero.
Cursive also to zero.
Weight to 600 to get a little bit heftier in the weight
and the slant to minus 10.
At 75%, I'll set the casual back to zero.
The cursive remaining at zero.
The weight at 300
and our slant at minus 10.
And since I'm going to have
this animation repeating infinitely,
I will make our 100% key frame equal to our 0% key frame
so that way it'll start and end in exactly the same place.
Last but not least,
I'll assign this animation to our h1.
So we'll give it animation of VARS
and I'll have it take eight seconds.
Make it a little bit long.
Have it repeat infinitely
and I'm going to use the easing of linear
just so we can really get a sense
of how the variable font itself is changing
and animating as it goes.
So we can save this
and preview it in our browser, refresh.
And you can see we have our h1 that has the word hello in it
animating through the variations of the axis we adjusted
through our key frame animation.
There's so much potential in what we can do
with animating variable fonts
and they allow us to create animation effects
that wouldn't be possible without them.
But I should note that at the time of recording,
variable fonts are still fairly new,
so there are a couple of things to keep in mind
if you're using them for animation.
First is that not all variable fonts are created equal.
Some may have very interesting axes
for you to animate for creative effects
while others may have a very limited range.
It might take a bit of time
to find the ones that have the range you like.
The second is that animating variable fonts
is currently not very performant,
so it's best to use it sparingly in production.
This might change as variable fonts see more use,
but keep an eye on your animation performance
if you're using variable font animations in your projects.
Variable fonts are very interesting
to experiment with for many reasons,
so I highly recommend checking them out
and taking a look at the power they bring to the web.