- [Val] The web design community is full
of helpful people.
And because of that,
we've got a lot of great online tools
to help you create CSS animation.
We've touched on some of these tools throughout the course,
and now we'll look at them all in one place.
For custom or expanded easing options,
cubic-bezier.com and easings.net have you covered.
On cubic-bezier.com,
you can edit the handles and adjust to your own curve
and even preview it right here on the site,
as well as copy and paste it for use in your own work.
Easings.net lets you preview a number
of commonly used easing equations,
including the power equations or Penner's equations
as they're sometimes called.
You can preview each of these to see how they look
and also copy the CSS for use in your own work.
For optimizing your SVGs before animating them,
svgomg is my go-to SVG optimization tool.
This is the browser-based version
and you can also use other formats of it as well,
but this one is my favorite.
And speaking of SVG,
if you want to do more extensive SVG animation,
I highly recommend using
the JavaScript animation library, GreenSock.
They have specialized plugins for SVG
like Draw SVG and Morph SVG
that can save you a whole lot of time.
Overall, I think it's the best animation library out there
to work with SVG animation right now.
If you're looking for some ready-made CSS animations
to jumpstart a project,
the next three sites are all great places to start for that.
Animate.css and animxyz.com feature an extensive collection
of ready to use CSS animation effects.
You can use them out of the box or build off them
to create your own animation effects
like you've learned in this course.
Animistic.net is similar to those last two,
but it also has a robust customization visualizer,
which can be really useful for learning
in addition to customizing the effect you want.
And last but not least,
browsing codepen.io is a great place
to find CSS animation inspiration,
and pick up on some new coding techniques.
I hope you'll find all of these sites useful
in your CSS animation work.