- [Instructor] So far, we've been creating animations
that play automatically on page load.
But there are definitely times where you might want to
change when an animation starts or temporarily pause
an animation while it's playing.
The animation-play-state property can be very useful
for both those things.
For this example, we're using this spinning
sub sticker image.
It's a little silly, but it totally works for what
we're demonstrating here.
We're going to use the animation-play-state property to have
this sub spin only when we're hovering over it.
And be paused when we're not.
We're using hover in this example,
because it's an easy input event for CSS to access.
But you might find that changing the animation-play-state
on events like click or scroll with the help
of JavaScript to be even more useful.
I've already got the keyframes for
the spinning animation here,
and we just saw it in action a minute ago.
But I can actually simplify these keyframes even further by
removing the 0% keyframe.
Without a 0% keyframe, the current styles on our element
will be used in its place.
And since our 0% keyframes weren't changing anything,
it was just a rotation of nothing,
that will give us the same results visually.
I've also assigned the rotate keyframes to our sticker,
giving it a duration of 10 seconds.
So it's a slow spin.
The animation timing function of linear.
And we're having it repeat infinitely.
We're using linear for easing here.
So there'll be no speed changes while it's spinning.
This is one of those cases where linear easing actually
looks better than some of the rest.
So let's move on to adding the play and pause functionality.
The thing we'll want to do is add the animation-play-state
property to our sticker so that the animation
is paused at first.
So we can do that by adding animation-play-state here.
And we're going to give it the value of paused.
If we save and preview our file right now, I'll refresh it.
You can see that our animation is paused.
Our sub sticker is not currently spinning.
Paused animations aren't as fun as ones that play.
So let's add the condition when our animation
will actively play.
To do that I'm going to start by adding a rule
for the sticker hover.
The two most useful values that the animation-play-state
property can take are the value of paused like we just used,
and the value of running.
So we'll add the value of running here.
While the animation-play-state.
And then a value of running.
So this means that when we're hovering over the sticker,
the animation-play-state will be changed to running.
Even though it's initially set to pause on our sticker
in the few lines above.
So if we save this and preview it now,
we'll refresh our page.
And our sticker is just hanging out there at first,
when we hover over it, it starts spinning.
And when we hover off it stops.
And you'll notice the animation just picks up
where it left off when we hover over it again.
You can use the same technique to play and pause a CSS
animation on other input triggers using JavaScript.
Or just start a whole group of animations playing
at the same time, or any other situation where you might
want to have one or more animations all start playing,
or all pause at the same time.
Animation-play-state is an often overlooked property
of CSS keyframe animations, but it has a lot of potential
to be useful in your animation work.