- [Instructor] Let's look at how we can use 3D Transforms
in our CSS key frame animations.
We'll create a short text effect like the one you see here.
By animating 3D Transforms on each letter
and using animation delay to create an offset
to have that wave like motion across our full text.
We'll be rotating each letter around the X axis,
which is the axis that runs horizontal
across the browser window.
In our HTML,
we have each letter wrapped in its own span
so we can target them individually.
There are helpful JavaScript libraries like Splitting JS
and others that will do this wrapping of each letter
in a span automatically for you at runtime.
But for the purposes of this example,
adding them manually works just fine.
So let's move to our CSS to start creating our animation.
Since I already know I'll be using 3D Transforms.
I'm going to start by setting two properties
on the parent H2 element to ensure that all of our letters
will have the same perspective and vanishing point
to make 3D effect look a little more convincing.
So the first property I'll add is perspective.
And the value I usually start with for this is 1000.
And perspective is essentially the distance away
that we are from the effect.
And I'm also going to add the transform style
of preserved 3D.
Next up, I'll start the key frames for this animation.
So I'm going to call this animation, flip up
because that's essentially what our letters will be doing.
And I know that I want to have the letters all start folded
back in space as if they're laying flat on the ground.
You know, like if there was a ground.
And then we'll have them rotate up
to the normal standing position.
To achieve this, I'll start with a rotation on the X axis
of 90 degrees.
And just to mix things up a little bit,
I'm going to use the from and two key words to define
our key frames instead of the percentages.
But are from keyword is the same as a 0% key frame.
So we'll add a rotation on the X axis of 90 degrees.
And then for our two key frame,
which is the same as a 100% key frame.
We'll add a rotation of zero degrees.
Our key frames are all set.
So let's apply this animation to our letters.
Now we know that all of our letters are wrapped in a span,
so we can apply the animation to all of them here.
We can say animation
and we're going to assign the animation of flip-up.
Since those are the key frames we just defined,
I'm going to give it a duration of one second.
And then I'm going to give it the timing function
of a custom cubic-bezier.
And I'm going to give it the animation film mode of both
since we will be adding some delays.
To create that wave lake offset effect,
we want each letter to start rotating up
just slightly after the one before it.
To accomplish that,
we'll add a delay to each letter after the first one.
And I'm going to add a very small delay of 0.2 seconds.
We'll target each subsequent letter using the Nth child rule
for our span.
So, this one is our second letter
and we'll give it an animation delay of 0.2 seconds.
And then we'll keep adding 0.2 seconds to our delay
for each subsequent letter.
So our third letter will have an animation delay
of 0.4 seconds.
And I'll keep going down the list.
If you're using a CSS pre-processor,
you can write a loop to take care of this in one fell swoop.
But for our example, I'm going to do it manually
since we only have a few letters.
With our delays in place,
we can save and preview our animation now.
We can see that our key frames and animation delay
are working as expected,
but our letters are all rotating from the middle
of themselves which is the default behavior.
The effect I was going for though was to have them seem
like they're rotating from the bottom of themselves,
as if they're sitting on a kind of imaginary floor.
So to do that, we're going to adjust the transform origin
for each of our letters.
The transform origin is the point around which transforms
are applied.
In our case, that's the rotation on the X axis.
And we're going to move it to a point
that's at the bottom of each letter,
instead of the middle of each letter
to create the effect we're going for.
Finding the exact transform origin values you want
often takes a bit of trial and error.
But I've done that ahead of time
and I know that I want to set my transform origin
for each of these letters to 50% of the way across
each letter's bounding box
and 70% of the way down.
Transform origin coordinates are always measured
from the top left when we're using percentages, pixels
or AMS.
So if we save that and preview our file once more,
we see that with that transform origin adjustment
our letters look like if they are rotating
from the bottom of themselves
and that creates the effect of them flipping up
from laying on the floor which is exactly
what we were going for.
So that's how to use 3D Transforms and key frame animations.
And how to use animation delay to create offsets
when animating multiple objects.
You can use both these techniques to create
all sorts of animated effects on text or HTML objects
in your own work.