- [Tutor] So far, we've been creating
mostly individual animations to create our effects,
but in practice,
you might want to combine multiple animations
to create the overall movement you're going for.
In this video,
we'll be adding to our up and over text animation
and we'll create one more set of key frames
to handle the over part of the up and over motion.
And the letters will end up hanging upside down.
Our HTML and CSS
are the same as we left them in the last video.
So let's head straight to our CSS
to add in the second set of key frames for us to use.
For this set of key frames,
I want the letters to flip down towards me,
so they end up upside down.
That's going to be a rotation on the X axis
of negative 180 degrees.
So I'll start this new set of key frames.
I'm going to call it flipDown.
And since we'll be using this set of key frames
to pick up right where the last set of key frames left off,
we can skip straight to the two key frame
or the end state of our animation.
So our two key frame will be a rotation on the X axis
of negative 180 degrees.
So that's flipping the letter all the way over.
Of course, after defining those key frames,
we'll have to assign them to our letters,
which we did here in the span rule.
And to add a second animation to this element,
we're going to use a comma to separate the two animations.
So we'll add a comma, and then flip down,
we'll give it a duration of one second as well.
And I'll use the same custom cubic-bezier.
And I'm going to give this second animation,
a very long delay.
Specifically 0.275 seconds.
And I chose 2.75 seconds because that's enough time
for all of the letters to perform their flip up animation,
have a little bit of a pause between the two animations
before this one takes place.
So when we're chaining two animations on the same object,
the way we have one happen after the other,
is by giving the second one a delay
that's equal to or longer than the duration
of the first one.
Last, but not least, I'm going to give this
animation film mode of forwards so that way our letters
will stay flipped upside down, once the animation is over.
We achieved the wave-like offset effect
for the flip up animation,
by giving each letter a slight delay
so that each letter would start just a bit
after the one before it.
We can add a second delay to all of our letters
to apply to the flip down animation,
to get that same effect there as well.
So I can go to my second letter
and just like we comma separated the two animations,
we can comma separate the two animation delays
to signify which animation each delay applies to.
In this case, since this is my second letter,
and I know my first letter is starting at 2.75 seconds,
I will give my second letter a delay of 2.95 seconds
so that it starts 0.2 seconds after the first one.
We'll use that same 0.2 second delay
throughout second animation as well.
And basically we just have to do a lot of adding
for those second delays.
So our third letter will be 3.15 seconds,
and on down the line.
And of course, if you're using a CSS pre-processor,
you could write a loop to automate these values,
but I'm doing it manually
since I have such a short number of letters
to add delays to.
With all those delays in place,
let's save and preview how our animation is looking.
We have the flip-up animation that we established before,
then we have a little bit of a pause,
and then our second flipped down animation
takes place on the letters,
leaving them upside down in the end.
It's worth mentioning that we could have pulled off
this same effect with one set of key frames,
essentially by duplicating the values in the middle
to create a hold frame.
But it's really up to your preference.
Personally, I prefer to split up the animations
because it gives me more flexibility.
For example, with these two sets of key frames,
if I wanted to change the delay value
for just the flip down animation,
that would be relatively straightforward.
So that's how to chain multiple animations on one element
using animation delay to space them out.
It's a great technique
for creating slightly more complex effects
or spacing out animations in time.
One word of advice, though,
if you find yourself creating a chain of animations,
that's more than three or four long in CSS,
that's a good time to consider moving to JavaScript
for your animation efforts.
Managing all those delays in order
can get really tedious in CSS.
And a JavaScript based animation solution,
will allow you to control a large number of animations
in a more robust and flexible way.