(bright music)
- [Instructor] Here's my solution to this challenge.
After the letters go up and down,
I added a little kick on the R
for a third animation in the chain.
I thought that would give it a little bit of,
I don't know, fun.
And here's what I did to add
that third animation to the chain.
First, I added one new set of keyframes in our CSS.
I called it flick
'cause that's kind of what the R is doing,
and I used a couple of tricks in this keyframe block.
First, since I knew I wanted the R
to start and end in the same place,
I comma separated the zero and 100% keyframes
to assign their styles at the same time.
You can use this anytime you're reusing properties
in two sets of keyframes.
The other thing I did was I chose
to set the animation timing function
in the keyframe definitions themselves
so that I could use a different easing
on the way out and the way in essentially
of that flick movement,
and this is something you can do
instead of adding just one animation timing function
across the entire animation, if you want to.
Once I had this third set of keyframes in place,
I went and assigned it to only the last letter,
which happens to be our nth-child seven.
Previously, we were having the flip up
and flip down animation assignments cascading
to all the spans and just setting the animation delay,
but since I wanted to add a third animation in the chain
just to this one letter,
I rewrote those animations,
comma separated them as we did before,
so that I could add the third one to the chain
just for this particular letter.
I assigned the animation of flicks
since that's what I named my keyframes.
I gave it a duration of .95 seconds,
and I delayed it by 4.95 seconds.
So again, a little bit longer
than the duration of the one before it,
so there is a bit of a break in between.
I assigned it the animation timing function of linear
since I specified animation timing functions
in the keyframes themselves,
linear is the best choice here,
and I gave it the animation film mode of forwards
so it would hold its end position
past the end of the animation.
So that was my solution.
Again, this is a challenge
where there's no right or wrong answer.
Whatever you did to add a third animation to the chain
was great practice in making CSS animations.