- [Instructor] Whether you're planning
to use CSS or JavaScript to animate your SVG in the end,
you'll want to make sure your SVG file is set up
in a way that's going to be good for animation.
There are many ways to draw shapes in SVG,
and your ability to animate the shapes you see
in a particular graphic depend on how the SVG was drawn.
It's useful to take a look to make sure
you have the pieces you need to animate.
That could save you a lot of headaches later.
The first thing you'll want to do is look
for distinct whole objects that you could translate,
rotate, or scale within the SVG.
I have an example SVG here from Undraw
that we can use as an example.
To inspect the SVG a little more closely,
I opened it in my vector editor of choice.
For me, that's XD,
but you can do this in any vector editing software.
So for example, as I click around the layers,
I can see that this check mark is an independent object,
so if I wanted to animate that I could,
and the square behind it is as well.
And those are probably two of the things I would animate
if I was animating this illustration.
So those are looking good,
but it is possible for things to look like separate shapes,
but not actually be separate shapes.
For example, if I wanted to animate the kind of body
of this avatar and head of this avatar,
I can't because they are actually together in one path.
And we can tell because when I go to move one of them,
both of them move,
and they are both part of this path called path 198.
So if I wanted to animate those separately,
I would need to edit this illustration further
to separate that path,
or possibly find a different illustration
that has those things separated out
depending on what I wanted to do.
In this case, I know I only want to animate the checkboxes
and that big rectangle behind those avatars,
so I know I'll be fine.
My second tip for checking your SVG
is to name the layers or the paths,
depending on how your file is set up,
that you'll be animating so it's easier to find them later.
To animate an SVG, we need to have it inline in our HTML.
If we name the shapes we plan to use in our animation,
it will be a lot easier to find them
and target them with CSS rules
when we're writing the animations.
So I'll go back to XD,
and I'm going to name this first check, check1,
and this box, maybe checkbox1,
and I'll do the same for the second box,
and the second check mark.
And I think you're getting the idea here.
I'll go through the rest of my layers now
and make sure that everything I'm planning on using
in my animation has a name so I can find it later.
You don't need to worry about naming
every single object though,
just the ones you know you'll want to use in your animation.
Most SVG illustrations have a whole lot of elements in them,
far more than you'll want to take
the time to name individually,
especially if you're not going to use
all of those objects in your animation.