- [Instructor] To animate your SVG
you'll need to have an inline in your HTML,
so you'll want to take a slightly different approach
to exporting and optimizing it than you might otherwise.
You'll want the code to be readable
and manageable while you're working on your animation.
Different vector editing tools
serve as different levels of options for exporting SVGs,
so you might see different options
depending on the tool you're using.
The main things you'll have options for when exporting SVG
are a choice between
presentation attributes or internal CSS,
a choice between linked images or embedded images,
and the option to minify the SVG file.
Let's look at each of these options more closely
to see what they mean for our exported code.
That first option on my list lets you choose
whether you prefer to have
your SVG's fill and stroke attributes displayed in CSS
at the top of your file
or as presentation attributes directly on the SVG elements.
The choice here is mostly up to personal preference.
Both are flexible in similar ways
and it just kind of comes down to what you prefer
or what's most useful for the way you tend to work.
If you choose the CSS option,
you'll get a block like this at the top of your SVG file.
This makes for an easy central place
to make changes to your strokes and fills as needed
and you can copy and paste the CSS
directly into your CSS file as well.
This is my preferred option.
But like I said, it's really up to personal preference.
If you select presentation attributes,
that same information that's in the CSS
will instead be attributes on the elements themselves.
So for example, this path has the fill set directly on it
as opposed to in a block of CSS at the top of the SVG file.
Next on the list is the question
of linked or embedded images.
Personally I rarely have images
embedded in my SVG files that I'm animating.
But if you do,
it's important to know that choosing embed here
will result in a higher file size,
so link is generally the best choice.
Linked images will also give you a greater flexibility
to change the image without re-exporting the entire SVG.
The biggest one to look out for
is the last one on my list about minifying.
Minifying your SVG might sound
like a good idea for file size,
but you'll want to keep the code
human-readable while you're animating,
and minified code is pretty impossible to read.
You can always modify the file later
once your animation is finalized,
but I highly recommend not minifying
while you're in the process of working on your animation.
With all that in mind,
I'll head to XD to export my SVG file from the last video.
So I will go here.
I'm going to do File, Export, and Selected.
And as I said,
I'm going to select Internal CSS.
I'm going to select linked images
even though it doesn't matter for this particular one
'cause I have no images
and I'm going to leave the minify unchecked.
I'll export my SVG
and then we'll move on to our next step
of optimizing that SVG.
Optimizing your SVG after you've exported it
is a good next step
because optimizing can lead to better performance.
My current SVG optimizer of choice
is Jake Archibald's SVGOMG.
I like that it's easy to access in the browser
and it lets you switch between the code
and image preview views
so you can make sure your optimizations
aren't adversely affecting any visual things in your SVG.
Once I'm here, I can upload my SVG
just by dragging and dropping it on the site,
and you'll see my SVG just like we saw in XD.
There are some default optimizations
already made for us here
and I'm not going to go through every option here.
But there are a couple of settings
you'll want to watch out for
when you're optimizing for animation.
The first is this one, Shapes to smaller paths.
Small is generally better when you're looking
to save file size
but this setting may fundamentally change
the nature of the objects in your SVG,
and that can make them harder to target for animation.
So use this one with caution.
If your animation relies on having things like circles
and rectangles in your SVG,
you'll want to turn this off
because it will turn those circles
and rectangles into paths.
In many cases that won't make a difference,
but it's one to look out for just in case it does for you.
The same goes for this Merge paths option.
If you're planning to animate any of your paths,
double check that this setting doesn't merge
any paths you need to keep separate
before going through with the optimization.
Merged paths generally means fewer paths.
But if you needed those individual paths to animate them,
that could be a problem.
You'll also want to keep an eye
on this Round or rewrite paths.
Keeping this turned on is usually fine,
but it can cause distortions in the shapes of an SVG
especially if that SVG is drawn at a very small size.
Most of the time,
the default settings are exactly what you need
and everything looks good both visually
and in the Markup tab.
Once you've got your settings in place
and everything looks good to you,
you can either download your SVG using the Download button
or you can go to the Markup tab
and copy and paste the code of your SVG
directly into your project.
Either way, your SVG is optimized and ready to use.