- [Instructor] Let's take what we know about CSS animation
and apply it to SVG elements too.
We'll create this heart filling animation
with this SVG heart to create an effect that you might see
when liking a post or photo or something like that.
My SVG code is inline here in my HTML.
This is our SVG.
And inside our SVG, we have two main shapes.
We have our heart outline
that I've given the idea of outline,
and we have our heart fill
that I've given the idea of heart fill.
We're working with a simplified SVG for this example,
an SVG with just two shapes,
but CSS animations can be applied to SVGs with more shapes
and more complexities as well.
We're just keeping it focused for this example.
Over in my CSS,
I have the two sets of key frames we'll be using
to create this animation.
The first is a set of key frames I've called beat,
and we'll use this on the fill shape of the heart.
It will take the fill shape starting very, very small,
a scale of 0.1, and then at 80% of the animation,
it will scale the fill shape up to be bigger than normal,
a scale of 1.25.
And at the end of the animation,
the heart fill will go back to its intrinsic size
with a scale of one.
I also have a set of key frames named fade,
which I'll be using on both the outline
and heart filled shape.
These key frames take whatever element I apply it to
from the opacity of one to an opacity of zero.
So let's apply these key frame animations
to our SVG elements.
Since our SVG is in line,
we can target its internal objects like our two heart shapes
with CSS selectors.
Like we saw in the HTML, I gave them both IDs,
so these are the two selectors I'll use
to target those internal SVG shapes,
the heart fill and outline, like the IDs I gave them.
Our filled heart shape is the one with the ID of heart fill.
So I'll start applying the animations to that one first.
And I know I'm going to use the beat animation
as I described.
I'll give that a duration of 0.8 seconds
and the easing of linear.
Then I'm going to use a comma to separate the two animations
because I want to apply the fade to the shape as well.
I think it'll look a lot nicer if it kind of fades in,
instead of just appears even when it's starting
at that very small size.
So we'll apply the fade key frames.
I'll give that a very short duration of 0.25 seconds.
And I'm going to have that set of key frames play
in reverse so it fades in.
And I'll give it the fill mode of both.
So that should take care of our heart fill scaling up
and in to view.
But if we save and preview our file now,
things may not look exactly as you expected.
And here we've run into one of the big things
that makes animating SVG elements different
from animating dom elements
and that's the SVG coordinate space.
The complexities of SVG coordinate space are more
than we can get into in this course.
But the key point to know is that the origin point
of SVGs coordinate system is at the top left.
And that's also the point from which SVG child elements
will transform from by default.
And that's what we're seeing here.
It's coming from the top left instead of the middle
of the heart shape itself.
Luckily we can make some adjustments in our CSS
to make the heart scale from the middle of itself
instead of the top left of the SVG.
And there are two properties I'm going to use to do this.
The first is setting a transform origin of 50% 50%,
which essentially says use a transformed point from 50%
across the element and 50% down the element,
so the middle of the element.
This new transform origin point though,
will still typically calculate from the SVG itself.
So that top left position.
So we can add one additional property
to tell the heart shape to calculate is transform origin
from within the shape itself
instead of the SVG it's a part of.
And that property is the property of transform box
and we'll set this to fill box.
And this means that the transform origin will be calculated
based on the fill box of our heart shape.
And that's more the look that we want.
So if we save now with those two properties added
and refresh our heart animation,
our heart is now scaling up from the middle of itself
instead of the top left of the SVG.
As one last step, I'll add the fade key frames
to our heart outline shape as well.
That way it will fade out as the fill is scaling in,
just for a little subtle difference on the effect.
So I gave that shape the ID outline,
and I'll add an animation to it.
I'll give it the animation of fade.
I'm going to have the animation take 0.25 seconds,
and I'm going to delay it by 0.4 seconds
so it doesn't start fading out quite right away.
I'll give it the easing of linear
and the fill mode of both as well.
So now when we save that
and preview our animation once more,
we can see that subtle difference of the outline fading out
just before the fill fully scales in.
So there you have it.
We've animated SVG elements with CSS,
and that's pretty powerful.
Animating SVG with CSS is useful
for small bits of animation.
But if you're planning on doing a lot of SVG animation,
I highly recommend using a JavaScript solution
like GreenSock or another JavaScript animation library.
JavaScript animation libraries and especially GreenSock
are built to take care of the common quirks
of animating SVG for you right out of the box.
So using one of them can save you a lot of time and effort.