- [Instructor] Both Chrome and Firefox browsers
have some very useful animation debugging tools
within their developer tools.
These tools can be extremely helpful
both in debugging and designing your CSS animations.
They let you see what's going on in the code
behind any given CSS animation.
Let's take a look at Firefox's tools first.
I have one of the animations from earlier in this course
open in my Firefox browser.
To get to the animation tools,
you need to open the web developer tools,
which you can do from the tools menu,
to browser tools and web developer tools,
or you can use the keyboard shortcut.
Depending on the layout of your web developer tools,
you may need to go to this arrow
and make sure animations is checked
to be able to see it in this right-hand pane.
And I'll also make mine just a little bit bigger
so I can see all the sections at once.
The details in this tab will only show up
once an element or elements have played their animation,
so you might need to refresh your page
to get them to show up.
Once I do, you'll see that my animations pane
has been populated,
and we can see the element that an animation is applied to.
We can see the name of the animation
and some general information about it here.
And in this bottom pane, we can see more information
around which property is being transformed,
and we can even hover over each individual keyframe
to get the values of that property
at each of these keyframes.
And if you don't see this lower pane initially,
you can just click on that top listing of the animation.
From here, we can also scrub through the animation
and we can even have it play at different speeds,
either very slow or very fast.
And I find that playing animations in slow motion
can be especially useful for debugging them.
One last thing to point out
that we'll see in the middle pane
when we have the animating element selected,
and I'll just refresh
so we get our animations populated again,
is the easing editor right here.
So on this little gray icon,
we can open the timing function editor,
and this will let us play
with different cubic-beizer easing options
right within our browser,
so that's a pretty neat tool as well.
And this tool can be especially helpful
when you're trying to get the easing just right
for a particular animation.
So that's a look at the animation tools in Firefox.
Let's take a look at the ones we have available to us
in Chrome as well.
I have this same animation open in Chrome now,
and to get to the Chrome developer tools,
we want to go to view, developer, and developer tools.
To open up the animation specific pane,
you need to go to this three dots menu on the right,
go to more tools,
and then animations,
and you'll get the animation pane opening up below.
I'm going to make my dev tools just a bit bigger
so we can see what's going on.
The first thing you'll see is a message saying
listening for animations,
and you'll need to trigger your animations
with this panel open to inspect them.
So I'll refresh the page
and now we'll see a little thumbnail
which represents our animation.
So we can click on that thumbnail
to see the animation that it captured.
If you have multiple animations going on on your page,
you might see multiple thumbnails,
but we only have one animation so we only see one thumbnail.
Clicking on the thumbnail opens up the timeline
for that particular animation.
And we can see things like its name, its overall duration,
the placement of the keyframes and the easing used.
We can also play and pause animation
or have it play back at different speeds
just like we saw in the Firefox Inspector.
In the Chrome Inspector, we can also do things
like move the keyframes around in time.
But note that any changes you make in this Inspector
will not be saved anywhere.
So you'll want to make note of any changes
you make in this panel.
Chrome also has a handy easing editor that you can access
from the elements property listing.
Look for this dark gray icon next to any easing assignment
to open the cubic-bezier editor.
And you'll see some very similar functionality
to what we saw in the Firefox editor,
where we can look through some easing presets,
see a little preview and even adjust the handles ourselves
to create custom easing right here in our browser.
Both of these animation inspectors are hugely helpful
for debugging and designing web animation.
They've saved me a lot of headaches
when animations just weren't playing back as expected
and I'm sure there'll be just as helpful for you too.