- [Instructor] Transforms, transitions, and animations
are all things that CSS can do,
but their names are so similar
they can sometimes be confusing.
All three terms sound like
they could possibly make things move,
but not all three of them do.
The focus of this course is on CSS keyframe animation.
But since all three of these
are frequently used together in web animation,
we'll cover transforms and transitions briefly as well.
Let's dive into transforms first.
I like to think of these as the yoga of CSS.
We can use them to bend and twist
those flat rectangular HTML objects
into all sorts of configurations.
I'll use this robot image here
to demonstrate some of the things that transforms can do.
Transforms are often used to translate
or move an object around the browser window,
so we'll start with that.
For example, in our CSS,
we can apply a transform of a translation to our robot
to move it slightly across the screen.
So we'll add a transform
of a translation on the x-axis
and we'll move this image 300 pixels to the right
on the x-axis.
The x-axis is the horizontal one.
So when we save this and go back to refresh our browser,
we'll see that our robot image
has moved 300 pixels to the right.
Translations can take other units as well,
like amps and percentages, for example.
But know that for transforms,
the percentage refers to the object itself,
not as container.
So if we go back to our CSS
and change that 300 pixels to 100%,
when we save and refresh our page once more,
we'll see that our robot has moved to the right
the equivalent distance of its own width,
which happens to be slightly less than 300 pixels
in this particular case.
We can also translate on both the x and y-axes
by using the translate function
and giving it two coordinates.
So for example,
we can change this translate x to just translate
and then give it two numbers:
the first one for the translation on the x-axis
and the second for the translation on the y-axis.
So we can say 100 pixels on the x-axis
and perhaps 200 pixels on the y-axis.
So when we save that and refresh our robot once more,
the image has moved slightly over 100 pixels to the right
and down 200 pixels.
Transforms can also scale and rotate objects
in addition to translating them.
We can also perform those on both the x and y-axis
at the same time or separately.
So let's add some rotation and scale to our robot
and see what happens.
I'll add a scale of two after our translation
and then a rotation of 45 degrees.
So that will make our robot double in size,
the scale of two, and rotate it 45 degrees.
If we save that and refresh our page once more,
we'll see that our translation stayed in place
and our robot is now twice its size and rotated 45 degrees.
Notice how each time we refresh our page,
our robot shows up in a slightly different
position and scale and rotation,
but we never see any movement or anything like that.
Transforms will change how our object appears,
but they won't create animation.
Transforms have a stacking order,
which means the order you apply each transformation in
will affect the overall look.
Each additional transformation is compounded
on top of the ones that have come before it in the list.
So if we go back to our CSS
and change the order of these transformed functions,
we'll see a slightly different result.
So for example, I can take this rotation
and move it to the beginning of our transform list.
And then maybe I'll also take the scale
and move it before the translation as well.
And now when we save that and refresh our page,
our robot is in a slightly different position
because our transforms were applied in a different order.
So that goes to show that it's important to remember
when we're using the transform property like this,
that the order of the transform functions
will affect the end result.
I should note that some browsers are starting to support
independent transform properties
behind an experimental flag.
But at the time of recording,
this isn't yet widely supported
so we'll be using the single transform property
like we just saw in this example.
So that's a quick look into transforms
and how you can use them
to change the appearance of elements on your page.