- [Instructor] One of the most interesting things
about CSS transforms is how easily they allow us
to create the effect of 3D.
I'll be touching on the basics
of 3D transforms in this video,
but there are other CSS courses in the library
that cover this in much more depth as well.
Getting to 3D in CSS
can be as straightforward as just rotating
around the x or y-axis.
Doing that angles part of the object
on screen away from you
and that makes you get a 3D effect.
I'll use this robot image to demonstrate.
It's just an image sitting in a HTML page,
but I can still apply 3D transforms to it.
In my CSS file,
I'll add a transform rule to our robot image.
So we will transform this
and we will give it a rotation on the x-axis of 45 degrees.
In browsers, the x-axis is the one that runs horizontally,
so it's essentially like we are rotating around a pole
going through the middle of this image.
If we save this and preview it in our browser,
it may not be exactly what you were expecting.
It looks a little bit misshapen
and not quite right just yet.
To get 3D transforms to look right
or at least as we expect,
we need to add some perspective.
Going back to our CSS,
there are two places we can add perspective.
We could add it to the transform rule itself
or we can set the perspective property on a parent element.
I prefer to set this on the parent element.
That way if I decide to add any additional elements
for 3D transforms later,
they'll use the same perspective setting.
So I'll go up to my parent element
which in this case happens to be my body
and I will add a perspective of 1,000 pixels.
The perspective length can be set in pixels or ems
and it represents an approximation
of how far away you are from the transforming element.
Lower values show a more drastic effect
and higher values show a flatter effect.
So if we save and preview our 1,000-pixel perspective,
the rotation looks a little bit
more like you were expecting.
We get that kind of 45-degree lean back feel to it.
To contrast, take a look at what that same rotation
looks like with a 100-pixel perspective.
So if we go back and change our 1,000 pixels to 100 pixels,
the effect is much more dramatic.
Rotating around the y-axis will get you a similar result
as just rotating on the up and down or vertical axis,
and you can also rotate around both the x
and y-axis for a combined effect.
So we can add an additional rotation
on the y-axis of 20 degrees
and I will also go back and change that perspective
to 1,000 instead of 100
so we can be a little bit less drastic.
When I save and refresh that,
you can see we have rotation on both the x and y-axis
and we've transformed this robot
a little bit more within 3D space.
You can also move objects in 3D space
using the translate3d function.
The translate3d function takes three numbers,
one for each of the x, y, and z-axes.
So if we go back to our CSS,
we can add a translate3d
and we can move our robot say 100 pixels on the x-axis,
200 pixels down on the y-axis,
and minus 100 pixels on the z-axis.
So essentially what this will do
is move our robot slightly over to the right by 100 pixels,
slightly down by 200 pixels on the y-axis,
and slightly back in space
with that negative 100 pixels on the z-axis.
So if we save and preview our robot now,
it kind of looks like our image just got smaller.
It should, it's further away from us now,
but it's difficult to see that distance
when we just have one object on screen.
Translations like this are much more visually effective
when they're animated or transitioned
so we can see that movement backward into space.
So that's a dust a short look at what CSS transforms can do
to give us a look of 3D space.