- [Narrator] CSS transitions are one of the ways
we can create animation with CSS
even though they're not called animations.
It's confusing, but true.
By definition, animation means causing change over time
and transitions absolutely do that.
They just do it in a different way
then CSS key frame animations do.
Let's start with creating a button
that transforms on hover
to take a quick look at what CSS transitions can do.
Transitions need a beginning and end state
to transition between, that's why we tend to use them
for things like hover states.
The initial styles on our element,
like what we're seeing here, are the beginning state
and the hover states we define end up being our end state.
So let's start by defining our hover state first.
We'll go to our CSS and a hover state for our button
and on hover, I'd like to have this button
both grow a little bit and change color.
So we'll add a transform
with a scale to have that growing
and we'll make it 1.3 so it'll grow just a little bit
and we'll add a background color to change the color,
and I'm going to change this to that same purple
that we have on the border of the button.
And then to make sure we have good contrast,
I will also change the color of the text.
So if we save that in preview our page now,
we have our hover state but it's just a hard cut
to those change properties.
There's no nice animated change that we wanted to see.
So let's go back to our CSS and add a transition
to smooth things out.
We apply the transition property to our button directly.
It's kind of like we're setting a property to say,
hey button, if any of your properties happen to change
in the future, here's how you should handle it.
So add a transition to our button and the minimum we need
for a transition is a duration,
so we'll set the duration to 0.5 seconds here.
This is probably a good time to stop and note
that we can use both seconds or milliseconds
for durations in CSS.
Milliseconds are one one thousandth of a second,
so 0.5 seconds is the same as 500 milliseconds
and 500 milliseconds is the same as 0.5 seconds.
In most cases, it's just a matter of preference
as far as which one you prefer to use.
So if we save this and go back and preview our button
once more, we can see a nice smooth transition when we hover
on and off our button.
Notice how setting that single transition
animates both the movement into the hover,
as well as back to the initial properties
when we hover off the button.
Right now, both our changing properties
are transitioning at the same time,
but we can have even more granular control
over our transition effects by giving each property
its own transition values.
So let's first assign a transition
to just our background property.
We can have that take 0.3 seconds and give it an easing
of ease-in.
Then we comma separate the transitions
for our separate properties and we can go
and have a separate transition defined
for our transform properties.
And we'll have this one take slightly less time
of 0.2 seconds and give it an easing of ease-in-out.
When you're writing multiple transforms,
make sure to comma separate the different rules.
Now, when we save and preview our button one more time
our background color and scale transform
change at slightly different rates.
Just by separating out
these two different transitioning properties,
we've created a slightly more nuanced effect.
Transitions can also be delayed,
so let's add a delay to just one
of our transitioning properties to see how that changes
the look of things.
In the short hand notation I'm using,
the second time-based value will be used
as the transition delay.
So I'll add a 0.1 second delay to the transition
on our transform property.
So this first time-based value, the 0.2 seconds,
is our duration for our transition
and that second time-based value, the 0.1 seconds,
is the delay for our transform transition.
So we'll save that and preview our button one more time.
And now we can see that our scale transform
starts transitioning just a little bit
after our background color starts changing.
So that's the basics of how we can create
some simple state-based animation with CSS transitions.
There are a whole lot of interesting animated effects
you can make with transitions.