(upbeat music begins)
- [Narrator] For my solution,
I added an additional transition
to the border radius property,
so my hover now looks like this.
To show you what I did, I'll go back to my CSS file.
And what I did was add a border radius of 20 pixels
to the button's hover styles.
And then I added an additional property
to the transition for border radius.
I gave it a duration of 0.3 seconds,
just like our background color,
and the same easing of ease in like our background color,
just to have a couple of things
line up with the same timing and easing.
And then the end result is what we saw here.
And there we have a hover effect
with one more transitioning property,
and some practice with CSS transitions.