- Motion design is quickly becoming
a core skill for web designers.
Designers and developers are realizing
the power of web animation to engage, delight,
and communicate with their users.
I'm Val Head and I'll be leading you
through this course on CSS animation.
I've spent much of the last few years helping folks to learn
how to make web animation work for them
and to get their brand in motion in a meaningful way.
I'm the author of Designing Interface Animation
published by Rosenfeld Media,
and I'm excited to introduce you
to the world of CSS animation.
This course is for web designers and developers
who have some experience with CSS
and want to take their understanding of CSS animation
to the next level.
I'll show you how CSS can be used
to animate both HTML elements and SVG.
We'll also discuss how to get the best performance
out of your animation,
as well as tools that will help you build
and troubleshoot your animation work.
Over the past few years,
web animation has grown into a powerful option
for enhancing the user experience on the web.
CSS animation is the perfect place to get started.