- [Narrator] Let's get started with some
CSS keyframe animation.
In this lesson, we'll create a simple animation
of tech scaling up into view with a little bit
of an overshoot to demonstrate the main components
of CSS keyframe animations.
The HTML behind our example is pretty straightforward.
Our text is in H2 sitting within our container div.
If we move to our CSS file, we have some text sizing rules
and some basic positioning going on, and that's about it.
So let's start adding some animation.
There are two main parts to any CSS animation.
We need to define the animation keyframes
in the @keyframes rule, and then we need to assign
those keyframes to a specific element or elements.
You can do these two steps in any order,
but I prefer to define the animation first
and then assign it to something.
So moving to our CSS file,
we'll start by creating our CSS animation
by defining its keyframes using the @keyframes rule.
And we'll give this animation a name because otherwise
we won't be able to assign it later,
and we'll call this one scaleIn
because that's essentially the effect we're creating.
Once we have our @keyframes block,
we define the values for the animating properties
at various points during the animation.
Any property that you want to have changed
over the course of one cycle of the animation
needs to be listed in your keyframes.
There are multiple options available for how to define
the keyframes within your @keyframes rule.
We can use key words like to and from
for keyframe animations that are animating
only between two states, but in my case
I'm going to use percentages to define my keyframes
for maximum flexibility.
The 0% keyframe or the "from" keyframe
represents the start of the animation
and the 100% keyframe or the "to" keyframe
represents the end state of the animation.
And we can use percentage values in between
to define as many additional stages of the animation
as we want along the way.
So I'm going to start our text at a small size,
say 20% of its full size or a scale of 0.2
for our 0% keyframe.
For this effect, I know I want it to grow
to be a bit oversized before it animates
back to its intrinsic size
to give it a bit of that overshoot feel.
So we'll add a scale of 1.1 or 110% of the given size
at the 85% keyframe.
And then, at the end of the animation
I want things to go back to their given size
or a scale of one,
so that will be our 100% keyframe.
And that completes our @keyframes block.
But if we previewed our file right now,
nothing would happen.
There would be no animation to see.
We've defined the keyframes for our animation
but we still need to assign it to a specific element
in order to see it in action.
To assign an animation to an element,
we give that element some additional CSS properties.
So in this case, that's our H2.
The first one we'll need to define is the animation name
and we'll set this to be the same thing we called
our keyframe block.
And this is essentially saying to our H2,
hey, use this specific set of keyframes,
the one we called scaleIn.
The second property we absolutely have to add
is animation duration.
Our keyframe block defines what will change
over the course of the animation
but we need to tell it how long to take as well.
So let's set this to two seconds.
Now when we preview our file
we see some animation happening.
We've just set the minimum needed to create
a CSS keyframe animation.
We've got the keyframes, we assigned it to an element
and we set a duration.
So now we've completed our first CSS keyframe animation,
our title scales up with a bit of an overshoot
and it's looking pretty neat.
Next, we'll look at some additional properties
that let us fine tune our animations for even more control
over the effect.