- [Instructor] Let's look at how properties
like animation-delay and animation-fill-mode
can help us do more with our key frame animations.
Both of these properties are ones I use a lot in my work
and I bet you'll find them super useful too.
We'll start with animation-delay.
It works exactly like transition-delay
except it's applied to key frame animations.
Animation-delay lets you specify a certain amount of time
that should pass before the key frame animation takes effect
on the object you've applied it to.
Let's add a delay to the text animation
we've been working on to see how it works.
We'll go to our h2 rule and add one more animation property,
and that property is animation-delay,
and I'll give it a delay of five seconds,
which is probably excessively long in most cases,
but that way, we'll really be able to see what's happening.
Now when we refresh the page,
there's a five second delay before animation starts.
However, it might not look exactly how you expected.
We see the text at full size
for those five seconds of the animation-delay.
The first key frame of our animation, that 0% key frame,
has styles to scale the text down to 20% of its normal size,
but that key frame styles are only applied
once the animation starts, not during any initial delay.
So that's why we see the text at full size
during those five seconds delay,
even though that's not where the animation starts,
and it's also where animation-fill-mode comes in handy.
The animation-fill-mode property essentially describes
how time around the animations actively play in duration
should be handled.
That means it lets you control what happens
during the delays before an animation starts
and also what happens after an animation's duration ends.
So if we go back to our CSS,
in addition to the animation-delay property,
I'm going to add an animation-fill-mode value of backwards.
The animation-fill-mode value of backwards
means that the styles from the animation's first key frame,
in this case, the 0% key frame,
will be applied backwards in time
to fill the time during our delay.
Now when we preview our text animation,
we see the behavior we were expecting
during that five second delay at the beginning.
I bet you're starting to see why animation-delay
and animation-fill-mode are two properties
that are used together so often.