- [Instructor] Animation-film-mode is a very useful property
for CSS animation, but it can be a bit confusing at first.
The way I like to think of it
is that the animation-film-mode property
determines how the time around an animation is filled in.
Animation-film-mode is set to none by default,
which is why you might notice that certain CSS animations
like this one here, jump back to their starting position
after an animation that moves them somewhere else
has completed.
The key frames behind that robot animation,
tell it to start from where it is
and to move 900 pixels to the right.
But once it finishes playing,
the robot goes right back to where it was
and that feels really weird at first.
I mean, we just told that to go over there,
but now it went back here,
and you might notice a similar behavior
during animation delays like we saw in the last video.
The reason for all this is that CSS animations
are temporal in nature.
Once the duration of the animation completes,
the styles in that animations key frames
are no longer acting on the element they animated.
That is, not unless we use animation-film-mode
to specify we want them to.
If you want your animating element to take on the styles
of the first keyframe of an animation,
in other words, if you want it to look
like the first keyframes property's already applied
during an animation delay,
set your animation-film-mode to backwards.
That will take the styling from the first keyframe
in the animation and kind of pull it backwards in time
during the animation delay.
On the other hand, if you want your animating element
to stay in place once an animation that moves it
has finished, or in other words,
you want the element to keep the properties
defined in the last keyframe of the animation
past the animation's duration,
set your animation-film-mode property to forwards.
That essentially takes the styles
from the last keyframe of the animation
and pushes them forward in time
or holds them forward in time.
However you prefer to think about it.
Conveniently, animation-film-mode
also has the option of both.
Which gives the behavior of forwards and backwards combined.
Personally, I tend to use both most often.
And I'll even assign it to all my animations
when I'm prototyping something
even if I'm not sure I need it yet.
It saves me that extra step
of wondering why things look funny
and having to go back and add it in later.
You might find that to be a helpful trick too.
In any case, know that if the element you're animating
isn't looking quite right during any animation delay
or after the animation has finished,
the animation-film-mode property
will most likely fix that for you.