- [Instructor] We've been talking about
the various properties outside of the keyframe definition
that we can use to change how an animation looks.
One of those properties that can be especially useful
for this is animation-direction.
Animation-direction lets us manipulate what order
our keyframes are executed in,
and we have a few different values
to choose from for this property.
We can set the animation-direction to normal,
which is default or reverse
or alternate or alternate-reverse.
Animation-direction is easiest to demonstrate
by animating position,
like the animation we're looking at here.
But now that this property can be applied
with any CSS keyframe animations,
not just one's animating position.
Right now, we've got our robot moving across the screen
from left to right using this set of keyframes.
You might notice the lack of a 0% keyframe here.
That's a handy trick you can use
when you want an object 0% keyframe styles
to be the same as whatever styles
are currently applied to that object.
If there's no 0% keyframe present,
the current styles applied to the object are used instead.
So our robot image starts
from where it was positioned intrinsically on the page
and animates a distance 700 times its width
on the X axis to the right.
If we look at the properties applied to our robot image,
you'll notice two things.
The first is this animation iteration count of three,
which is why we saw our robot
moving across the screen three times,
and you'll also notice that we have
no animation-direction set.
So we're seeing it animate with the default value
of normal for animation-direction,
which in this case is from left to right.
If we want our keyframes to execute in the opposite order
and have the animation play in reverse,
in that case, this would mean going from right to left.
We can add the animation-direction property of reverse,
and when we preview our robot now,
it's moving in the opposite direction.
That's pretty neat,
especially because we didn't have to adjust
any of the keyframe values to make this happen.
Of course, we aren't going to stop there.
We have two more possible values
for animation-direction to compare.
Let's give our robot the animation-direction value
of alternate instead.
Now this is one where animation iteration count of three
is very important.
To use the animation-direction of alternate,
you need to have more than one iteration happening
and you'll see why in a second.
When we save and preview our robot now,
you'll notice that the robot is moving forwards
and then backwards and then forwards again.
It's alternating its direction
each time the animation executes.
That's why it's so important
to have an animation iteration count higher than one.
Last but not least,
we'll assign our robot the animation-direction
of alternate-reverse.
When we save and preview that,
this gives us the same back and forth motion
as the last time,
except this time it starts playing
the reverse direction first and then the normal direction.
Again, it's important
for the animation iteration count property
to be higher than one,
otherwise there wouldn't be anything
to alternate and reverse.
Now you know the power of animation-direction
and how it can change up the look of your animation
without having to edit the underlying keyframes.
It's a property I'm sure you'll be using a lot
in your CSS animation work.