- [[Narrator] Easing is one of those things
that I don't think web designers talk about enough.
The easing you choose has the power to greatly affect
the way your animation is perceived
and what it communicates.
And that makes it an important factor of any animation.
By definition, easing is what describes
the speed changes of your animation
over the course of its duration.
Easing is used in many types of animation,
and there are almost endless variations
of easing functions out there.
In CSS, easing is handled by the animation
timing function property,
or the transition timing function property
if you're using transitions.
We have three options
for defining animation-timing-functions.
We have our predefined easing keywords,
the steps function, or custom cubic-bezier functions.
Let's start our look at easing and CSS
with the predefined easing keyword options.
The easing keyword options available in CSS are ease,
ease-in-out, ease-in, ease-out and linear.
These might all sound a little repetitive,
but they reflect common patterns you'll see
in all sorts of easing, even beyond CSS.
Let's go back to one of our robot animations from before
and see how these different
animation-timing-function keywords
can affect the way the animation looks.
I don't have an animation-timing-function defined yet.
So I'll add one to start things off.
And I'll start with a keyword of linear.
So we can save that, go to our browser,
to preview our robot, and here's what we see.
The robot moves across their screen,
and it stays at a constant speed the entire time.
Linear easing means there's no speeding up or slowing down
over the course of an animation.
Just one constant rate of change across the entire duration.
Linear is the default setting for easing
in many other animation tools, but not in CSS.
To get linear easing and CSS,
you have to set it explicitly like I just did.
Linear easing is often perceived as feeling very mechanical
since nothing in real life actually moves
at a constant speed like that.
To be fair, that could work for a robot,
but let's keep looking at our other keyword options
for easing to see how they compare.
If we change our robots, animation-timing-function,
to ease-in, we'll start to see some speed changes
over the course of its animation.
So I'll save this and go back to our robot,
refresh it again.
The robot starts out a little slow and then speeds up
towards the end of the animation when it stops abruptly.
It gives it a feel as if the robot is accelerating
into the movement and then reaching its top speed
near the end of the movement.
Any easing function that creates this behavior
of accelerating into the movement of the animation
could be considered an ease-in.
But the easing keyword in CSS refers
to one specific definition of easing in.
Next up on our list of CSS keyword easing values
is ease-out.
So we'll just change this a little bit,
then we can save and preview to see
how our robots movement has changed.
With the ease out keyword, our robot starts
at a high rate of speed and then starts to decelerate
or slow down before it comes to a stop
at the end of its movement.
Based on what we saw with those last two options,
I bet you're starting to guess
what the ease-in-out keyword will do.
So let's add that to our robot now.
Use the animation-timing-function of ease-in-out.
When we save that and preview our robot once more,
our robot both accelerates into its movement
and slows down before coming to a stop.
It's the behavior we saw with the ease-in
and the ease-out combined in one together.
We have one last easing keyword left to see.
And that's the keyword of ease.
So we'll go back and make our animation-timing-function
be just ease.
Ease is also the default value
for animation-timing-function.
So if you've been doing animation before
and haven't defined an animation-timing-function explicitly,
you are using ease and you just got it by default.
If we save our robot with the ease timing function,
and then go and preview it, to see how things look,
we can see a distinct speeding up into the movement
and slowing down before the robot stops.
But it's a little bit of a different speeding up
and different slowing down than we saw with the ease-in-out.
So both the easing we get from the ease keyword
and the easing we get from the ease-in-out keyword
are variations of the greater category
of the ease-in-out pattern.
The CSS keywords are a great way to get started with easing,
especially if you're brand new to it.
But there's even more we can do with easing and CSS.
Thanks to the cubic-bezier function.
Cubic-bezier functions are one of our options
for the animation-timing-function property.
Cubic-beziers may look a little bit unusual at first,
but we've actually been using them already.
Each of those keyword options can also be defined
by a cubic-bezier curve.
The keywords are a bit like a shortcut
to a specific cubic-bezier function.
For example, the cubic-bezier equivalent
of the ease-out keyword is this cubic-bezier function
we're looking at right now.
The four numbers in the cubic-bezier function
represent two X,Y coordinates.
As you can see here on cubic-bezier.com.
Sites like cubic-bezier.com, make it easier to visualize
what the values of the cubic-bezier functions we'll do
by showing you both the function itself,
as well as a graph view and a preview
of the easing in action.
So here's how the cubic-bezier graphs work.
The start and end points, or the graph are fixed.
Your animation does have to start, and it does have to end.
But the cubic-bezier curve describes what happens
between the start and end points in time.
Moving the two control handles
will change the number of the function
as well as the shape of the curve.
The curve indicates how fast or slow
the rate of change will be for the animating property.
Where the curve is steepest,
the rate of change will be fastest
and where the curve is flatter,
the rate of change will be slower.
So for example, this curve would start out slower,
it's a little bit flat and then speed up as it gets steeper.
The cubic-bezier function allows you to create
just about any variation of easing that you want to use.
Another great resource for a system
of cubic-bezier functions is on easings.net.
This site has both the graph and function representation
of commonly used power equations.
Also known as the Penner equations
translated to cubic-beziers and ready for you to use
in your CSS.
These same easing curves are available
in a lot of animation libraries as well,
so their names might look familiar.
While we're looking at easings.net,
I'm going to pick this one right here
and go and copy and paste it's cubic-bezier function
so we can use it on our robot.
Go back to my CSS, and then we can paste
that cubic-bezier function right here
for the animation-timing-function property.
With that in place, when we go back and preview our robot,
it's going to look just a bit different.
With that cubic-bezier function in place for easing,
we see our robot go a little bit past its destination,
kind of overshoot with a tiny bit of a bounce
and then settle back into place.
And that's all thanks to the cubic-bezier function
that we selected.
Now that we've taken this more in-depth look
into our easing options in CSS,
you'll be able to fine tune your animations
with easing choices that reflect the feel you want
your animations to have.
There's so much power to communicate
with the easing you select for your animations.
I encourage you to find a cubic-beizer editing tool
that works best for you and use them
in all of your web animation work.
It will make your animation efforts look
so much more expressive.