- [Tutor] We have one last timing function to look at,
and that's the steps function.
Steps work a little differently than our other options
for animation timing functions.
And they can seem a little confusing at first,
but here's how I like to picture it.
The steps function essentially splits the total duration
of your animation into equal blocks of time.
Each one of those blocks is a step.
Each of those tiny blocks also take up some amount of time,
even if it's just a fraction of a second.
So instead of continuous motion,
your animation is divided up into a series of holds
something like this.
And you can use the jumpstart and jump and keywords
for finer control over how the whole effect behaves.
Let's create a typing on effect animation
to get a feel for how steps works.
The basis of this effect is to animate the width
of our H1 to reveal the letters one at a time
as if they're typing on.
And that one at a time part,
is what steps will make possible.
So I already have things partly started
and I've written some key frames
that we'll use to animate the cursor blinking.
But we still need some key frames to make the type on effect
and essentially reveal the h1, one letter at a time.
So I'll start my @keyframes block,
and I'm going to call this animation typing.
And we'll set up these key frames,
very similar to how we've done in previous examples.
We want to start our h1 with a width of zero.
So our 0% key frame, we'll set the width of zero pixels,
and then we want it to end at its full size.
So start being basically invisible 'cause it's so thin
and end being wide enough to see all the letters.
So that's our 100% key frame
and we'll set the width there at 100%.
With those key frames in place.
We'll assign this animation to our h1.
So we'll give it the animation name of typing,
like we just had below.
And we'll give it an animation duration of three seconds
and we'll additionally,
give it the animation timing function of steps.
Now we have to give it a number of steps to take.
And in this case we have 14 letters.
So I'm going to use 14 steps, one for each letter.
So if I save that and preview our file,
we start to see our typing on effect.
The letters are appearing one at a time as the h1 expands
and that's thanks to the steps function.
There's one more thing we want to add
to get this full effect.
And that's the blinking cursor.
Right now, it's just kind of hanging out.
So let's give it an animation as well.
And we'll also use steps to get that blinking effect.
So we'll go back to our CSS.
And what we're going to do,
is apply both the blinking key frames
and the typing key frames to our h1.
The typing will adjust the width to show the letters
and the blinking will adjust the border color
on the far right side to create our cursor.
When we're applying more than one animation to an element,
it becomes a lot easier
if we start using the animation shorthand.
So I'm going to take what we've got right here
and replace it with the shorthand version,
to make it easier to add the second animation as well.
So, for our shorthand version,
we're going to use the animation property,
and we're going to give it the animation name of typing.
We'll give it a duration of three seconds.
The first number
with time associated with it in the shorthand
will be used as the duration.
And we know we want three seconds.
That's what we used before.
And I'll give it the animation timing function of steps.
And we use 14 there before, so we'll use 14 there again.
So this is the shorthand version of what we had written
a few seconds ago.
Now I'll a comma here to separate our two animations.
And I like to move to a new line
because it just makes it easier to read,
but that is completely optional.
So I'll add a second animation of blinking.
That's going to be for the cursor,
which is a border on our h1.
We're going to give it a duration of 0.5 seconds
because the blinking is going to happen rather quickly.
And we'll give it the animation timing function
also of steps.
And we're going to give this one, a step of one.
And we'll also tell it to repeat infinitely.
So that's essentially the animation iteration count
of infinite.
Because to look like a real cursor,
we want to have it blinking even after we stop typing.
So if we save this and preview it now,
we have our letters showing up one at a time
typing on thanks to our typing key frames animation.
And we have the cursor blinking
thanks to our blinking animation.
Both of which are powered by the steps timing function.
So that's our quick look
at the steps function for CSS animation
and the sort of look it can give your animations.
Steps don't tend to get used as often
as other timing functions,
but it's still good to know about for those times
when it's the right solution for what you need.