- [Instructor] Here's my solution to the adding
key frames challenge.
I replaced our scale in effect with a bit of
a wiggle effect.
Here's what I did in the CSS.
I created a new set of key frames and called it wiggle
since I was making a bit of a wiggle effect.
And in the key frames, I adjusted both the translation
on the X axis and the rotation to give it just a little bit
of a movement and a bit of a rotation back and forth.
Another thing I changed was the transform origin over h2.
And that makes the rotation look just a bit different
because we're rotating from a slightly different point.
Then I applied the animation of wiggle.
I gave it a quite short duration since wiggles generally
happen kind of quickly.
Had it repeat infinitely and used this cubic-bezier
for the easing.
There's no right or wrong answer for this challenge.
So whatever you did to adjust the key frames and create a
slightly different effect, you're on the right track.